ネット:network
（ヤサコ）ネットのウワサによると
メタバグの中には―
According to rumors on the Net,
it's said that
音[おと, ね]:sound|note|fame|, 映像[えいぞう]:reflection|video|image in one's mind, 情報[じょうほう]:information/news|information, 含む[ふくむ, くくむ]:to contain|to hold in the mouth|to bear in mind|
時として音や映像などの情報が
含まれているそうです
you can sometimes find data such as sounds or images inside metabugs.
それが どこから来たものなのかは
よく分かっていません
But nobody really knows where they come from.
たった:only/merely/but
（ガチャギリ）来た！
ハァ… たったの700メタか
Found it!
Only 700 meta?
デンパ:electromagnetic wave/radio wave/reception
おい デンパ 聞いてんのかよ
Hey, Denpa, are you listening?
波[なみ]:wave, 波[ぽ]:Poland, 音がする[おとがする]:to make a sound/to give off a sound|to hear a sound
（デンパ）
うん 聞いてるよ 波の音がする
Yeah, I am.
It sounds just like waves.
持つ[もつ]:to hold (in one's hand)|to possess|to maintain||, よこす:to send/to forward|to hand over (e.g. money)
（ガチャギリ）
まだ持ってたのかよ よこせ！
You still got that thing?
Give it to me!
聞こえる[きこえる]:to be heard/to be audible|to be said to be
なんも聞こえねえ
I don't hear anything...
たった:only/merely/but
ハァ… たったの50メタかよ
Only 50 meta?
せっかく:stone burial chamber, せっかく:with trouble/at great pains|rare, 音[おと, ね]:sound|note|fame|
せっかく いい音だったのに
But it sounded so nice.
いける:to arrange (flowers)/to plant|living, いける:to be good (at)/to go well|to look (taste, etc.) good, サイト:site (usu. website)
（女子生徒）
ガチャギリ！　あんた それ
見ちゃいけないサイトでしょ
Gachagiri!
You're accessing a forbidden site, aren't you?
サイト:site (usu. website), 事件[じけん]:event/affair/incident, 巻き込む[まきこむ]:to roll up/to enfold|to involve, 子供[こども]:child/children
前 そのサイトで
事件に巻き込まれた子供がいるって
I already told you that a kid got in trouble for doing that!
学校[がっこう]:school, 禁止[きんし]:prohibition/inhibition/ban, じゃん:isn't it
学校が禁止してるじゃん！
You know it's forbidden at school!
余計[よけい]:too many|unnecessary|abundantly, お世話[おせわ]:help/aid/assistance
知らねえよ！　余計なお世話だ
I don't care! And besides, it's none of your business!
文句[もんく]:complaint/grumbling|phrase
なんか文句あんのかよ！
What are you looking at?
（フミエ）ハラケン
あら フミエ
Oh, Fumie.
クラス:class
違うクラスのヤツ入ってくんな！
You're from another class, so don't come here!
べえ～！
次[つぎ]:next/following|stage, 次[じ]:next|hypo- (i.e. containing an element with low valence)|order, もっと:(some) more/even more/longer, 値段[ねだん]:price/cost, 高い[たかい]:high/tall|expensive, 拾う[ひろう]:to pick up/to find/to gather
次は もっと
値段の高いの拾ってこいよ
Next time, you have to find more valuable ones.
今度[こんど]:this time|next time|recently, クラッシュ:crash, 修理[しゅうり, しゅり]:repairing/mending/servicing
今度 クラッシュしたら
もう修理できねえぞ
If my glasses crash one more time,
I won't be able to pay for repairs.
紹介[しょうかい]:introduction/presentation/referral, 生物[せいぶつ]:living things/creature|biology, 生物[なまもの]:raw food/perishables, 部長[ぶちょう]:head (chief, director) of a section or department|head of a (school) club/head of a (school) team
（フミエ）紹介するわ
生物部の部長 ハラケンよ
I'll introduce you.
He's the Biology Club president, Haraken.
ちなみ:association/link|pledge (esp. for marriage), 副部長[ふくぶちょう]:deputy director/assistant director/vice director
ちなみに 私は副部長やってるの
I'm the vice president of the club by the way.
よろしく:well/properly|best regards
（ヤサコ）よろしくね
Nice to meet you.
よろしく:well/properly|best regards
よろしく
Same here.
無愛想[ぶあいそう, ぶあいそ]:unsociability/bluntness/surliness, 有名[ゆうめい]:famous|fame
無愛想なのでも有名よ
He's known for his unpleasant personality.
例[れい]:custom|said|instance|, 例[ためし]:precedent/example, ツアー:tour, 加える[くわえる]:to add|to increase|to include|
ハラケン 例のツアーに
この子を加えたいんだけど
Haraken, I would like to have her join us on that  trip.
（ハラケン）うん いいよ
Sure.
Sounds good.
イリーガル:illegal, 興味[きょうみ]:interest (in something)/curiosity (about something)/zest (for)
（ヤサコ）
私 イリーガルに興味あるの
I want to learn more about the Illegals.
部長[ぶちょう]:head (chief, director) of a section or department|head of a (school) club/head of a (school) team, 研究[けんきゅう]:study/research/investigation, くらい:dark/gloomy|dark (in colour), くらい:approximately/about|to (about) the extent that, イリーガル:illegal, 詳しい[くわしい]:detailed/full|knowing very well
部長さんは研究してたくらいだから
イリーガルのこと詳しいのよね？
And I know you've done some research on them, President,
so you must know a lot about them.
部長[ぶちょう]:head (chief, director) of a section or department|head of a (school) club/head of a (school) team, 紹介[しょうかい]:introduction/presentation/referral
でも部長を紹介したのは
それだけじゃないのよ
But that's not the only reason I introduced the two of you.
見せる[みせる]:to show/to display
ハラケン 見せて
Haraken, show her.
生物[せいぶつ]:living things/creature|biology, 生物[なまもの]:raw food/perishables, 長[たけ, たき]:height|length (esp. of clothing)|all (one has)|, 長[ちょう]:head|merit|superiority|, 仮[け]:lacking substance and existing in name only/something without substance, 仮[かり]:temporary|fictitious|hypothetical, 姿[すがた]:figure|appearance|state||
（フミエ）生物部部長は仮の姿
The position of president of the Biology Club is just a cover.
会員[かいいん]:member/the membership, 番号[ばんごう]:number/series of digits, 番[ばん]:number (in a series)|(one's) turn|watch|, 番[つがい]:(one) pair (e.g. of birds)/brace|joint
会員番号５番 ハラケンよ
He's actually one of our members. Number Five: Haraken.
部長[ぶちょう]:head (chief, director) of a section or department|head of a (school) club/head of a (school) team, 頼りない[たよりない]:unreliable/undependable|helpless
部長としては
ちょっと頼りないけどね
He's not really reliable as a club president.
夏[なつ]:summer, 夏[か]:Xia (dynasty of China; perhaps mythological), 狩り[かり]:hunting|harvesting (e.g. berries, fruit)/picking, ツアー:tour
（ヤサコ）夏の
メタバグ狩りツアー？
The summer metabug-hunt tour?
Metabug Scramble
Bus Tour
実[じつ, じち]:truth|sincerity|content|, 実[み]:fruit|seed|(in broth) pieces of meat, vegetable, etc.|, 情報[じょうほう]:information/news|information, つかむ:to seize/to catch|to obtain
実はね ちょっとした
情報をつかんだのよ
As a matter of fact,
I happened to get hold of some infor—
主催者[しゅさいしゃ]:sponsor/promoter/impresario, 参加[さんか]:participation, なさる:to do
あんた 主催者なんだから
参加しなさいよ
Hey!
You're coming with us, so get over here!
O-Okay...
街[がい]:.. street/.. quarter/.. district, 街[まち, ちょう]:town|street|109.09 m||, 大[おお]:big/large, 大[だい]:the large part of|big|approximate size||, 鉱脈[こうみゃく]:vein (of ore)/reef/streak, らしい:seeming ... (expresses judgment based on evidence, reason or trustworthy hearsay)/appearing ...|-ish
この街のどこかに まだ
メタバグの大鉱脈があるらしいのよ
I heard that somewhere in this town
there's still a lode of metabugs.
もしかし:perhaps/maybe/by some chance, こないだ:the other day/lately/recently, 掘り出す[ほりだす]:to dig out/to pick up
もしかしたら こないだ
イサコが掘り出したものも―
I'm not saying that the stuff Isako dug up last time
一部[いちぶ]:one part/one portion|one copy (e.g. of a document)
その一部かもね
wasn't a part of it either...
駅[えき]:station, 近く[ちかく]:near|nearly (e.g. "it took nearly one year")|shortly
（ヤサコ）
じゃあ 駅ビルの近くなの？
So it's located somewhere around the station building?
駅[えき]:station
（フミエ）
それが駅ビルには もうないのよ
I doubt there's anything left near the station.
Where then?
（ヤサコ）それじゃあ どこに？
（ダイチ）４年 どうだ？
Fourth year, any news?
場所[ばしょ]:place|room|basho
（アキラ）
はい 場所までは知らないようです
Yes.
Apparently, they don't know the location yet.
（ダイチ）
なんだよ 知らないのかよ
What? They don't?
もっと:(some) more/even more/longer, 集める[あつめる]:to collect/to assemble/to gather
ハァ… もっとメタバグ集めんとな
We have to collect more metabugs.
くらい:dark/gloomy|dark (in colour), くらい:approximately/about|to (about) the extent that, 集まる[あつまる]:to gather/to collect/to assemble
で どのくらい集まった？
So how many do we have?
入れる[いれる]:to put in|to admit|to accept||, お年玉[おとしだま]:New Year's gift (usu. money given to a child by relatives and visitors), 換算[かんさん, かんざん]:conversion (e.g. yen to dollars)/change/exchange, 半年[はんとし, はんねん]:half year, ぐらい:approximately/about|to (about) the extent that
今日の分 入れても
お年玉換算で… 半年分ぐらいだ
Including the ones we found today,
the equivalent in otoshidama is...
about half a year's.
損害[そんがい]:damage/injury/loss, くらい:dark/gloomy|dark (in colour), くらい:approximately/about|to (about) the extent that, 全員[ぜんいん]:all members (unanimity)/all hands/the whole crew
損害はどのくらいだ？
（ガチャギリ）全員で12年分
How much is it to repair the damage?
For all of us, twelve years'.
全然[ぜんぜん]:not at all (with neg. verb)|wholly/entirely, 足りる[たりる]:to be sufficient|to be worth doing|to be sufficient
全然 足りん！
It's not enough!
Damn transfer student...!
おのれ:oneself (itself, etc.)|I/me, 転校生[てんこうせい]:transfer student/student changing schools
おのれ 転校生…
大変[たいへん]:very|immense|serious||, 金欠[きんけつ]:running out of money
（イサコ）大変ね 金欠？
You seem to have a problem.
Strapped for cash?
昨日[きのう, さくじつ]:yesterday, 大変[たいへん]:very|immense|serious||
昨日は大変だったようね
Yesterday was tough, wasn't it?
てめえ:you (used by young males)|oneself
イサコ てめえ…
Damn Isako!
やめる:to stop (an activity)/to cease|to cancel, やめる:to resign/to retire/to quit, ちょうだい:receiving/reception|eating, ちょうだい:very long/great length
そのイサコってのは
やめてちょうだい
Stop calling me Isako.
手を貸す[てをかす]:to lend a hand/to help, あげる:to raise/to elevate|to do up (one's hair)
手を貸してあげようか？
I might as well help you out.
Wh-What did you say?
な… なんだと？
探す[さがす]:to search (for something desired, needed)/to look for|to search (for something lost)
そんなクズバグを探すより
Instead of looking for those rubbish-bugs,
よっぽど:very/greatly|just about to, 取り[とり]:taking|last performer of the day (usu. the star performer)|active partner (e.g. in judo demonstration)|, 取り[どり]:samurai receiving this much rice as a fee|offering of rice cake containing this much rice|person receiving this amount of money as a salary, 早い[はやい]:fast|early (in the day, etc.)|(too) soon|, 方法[ほうほう]:method/process/manner
よっぽど手っ取り早い方法が
あるんだけどな
there's a much faster and more effective way to collect metabugs.
どういう:somehow/how/in what way, 意味[いみ]:meaning/significance
どういう意味だ？
What do you mean?
大[おお]:big/large, 大[だい]:the large part of|big|approximate size||, 鉱脈[こうみゃく]:vein (of ore)/reef/streak, 在る[ある]:to be (usu. of inanimate objects)|to have|to be located||
メタバグの大鉱脈の在りかを
知ってるのよ 私
There's a big lode of metabugs, and I know where it is.
明日[あした, あす]:tomorrow|near future, お休み[おやすみ]:holiday|sleep|Good night
明日はお休みよね
And since we don't have school tomorrow...
朝[あさ, あした]:morning, 朝[ちょう]:dynasty|reign|period||, 集合[しゅうごう]:gathering/assembly|set
朝の10時に集合よ
Meet me here at ten o'clock.
始める[はじめる]:to start|to open (e.g. a store)|to start ...
（フミエ）
あいつ また何か始めるつもりね
She's up to something again.
What are you going to do?
どうするの？
狩り[かり]:hunting|harvesting (e.g. berries, fruit)/picking, ツアー:tour, 改め[あらため]:former (e.g. name)/previous|examination, 黒[くろ]:black|black go stone|guilt, 客[きゃく, かく]:guest/visitor|customer, 客[まろうど, まろうと]:visitor from afar/guest, 追跡[ついせき]:chase/pursuit|following up
メタバグ狩りツアー改め
黒客(ヘイクー)追跡ツアーだわ
Seems like our metabug-hunt tour will become a hacker-tracking tour instead!
And who is this "fourth year" anyway?
かしら:I wonder, かしら:head|hair (on one's head)
にしても
この４年ってのは誰かしら？
目的地[もくてきち]:place of destination
（フミエ）目的地はどこだろう？
I wonder where they're headed.
北[きた]:north|the North|North Korea|, 北[ペー]:north wind tile|winning hand with a pung (or kong) of north wind tiles, 鉱脈[こうみゃく]:vein (of ore)/reef/streak
北に鉱脈があるってウワサは
聞いてたけど
I heard somewhere that the lode is to the north—
黒[くろ]:black|black go stone|guilt, 客[きゃく, かく]:guest/visitor|customer, 客[まろうど, まろうと]:visitor from afar/guest
あっ… あの子 なんで黒客に？
Why is he with the hackers?
４年って
あの子のことだったんだわ
So he's the fourth year?
まったく:really/truly|indeed
まったく…
Oh geez!
早い[はやい]:fast|early (in the day, etc.)|(too) soon|
（ヤサコ）フミエちゃん 早いのね
Fumie.
You're here early.
隠れる[かくれる]:to hide/to be hidden/to conceal oneself
ど… どうしたの？
（フミエ）隠れて 隠れて
Wh-What's wrong?
Get down, get down!
ハラケン君は？
And Haraken?
遅刻[ちこく]:lateness/late coming, ホント:truth/reality/actuality, 頼りない[たよりない]:unreliable/undependable|helpless
遅刻よ ホント頼りないんだから
He's late.
You can't really rely on him.
抑える[おさえる]:to pin something down|to seize|to gain control of something|
だからダイチたちを
抑えられなかったのよ
That's why Daichi's group didn't keep him with them.
話[はなし]:talk/speech|discussions, 話[わ]:counter for stories, episodes of TV series, etc.
なんの話？
What are you talking about?
話[はなし]:talk/speech|discussions, 話[わ]:counter for stories, episodes of TV series, etc.
ああ その話
まだしてなかったわね
Oh, I forgot to tell you about that.
連中[れんちゅう, れんじゅう]:company/lot|troupe, 去年[きょねん, こぞ]:last year, 生物[せいぶつ]:living things/creature|biology, 生物[なまもの]:raw food/perishables
あの連中も
去年まで生物部だったのよ
Those guys used to be in the Biology Club too.
Sorry I'm late.
（ハラケン）お待たせ
（フミエ･ヤサコ）シーッ
カッコ:parentheses/brackets, カッコ:shape/form/figure, 悪い[わるい]:bad|evil|unprofitable||, 悪い[にくい]:hateful/abominable|amazing
（ナメッチ）オヤビ～ン
なんかカッコ悪いっすよ！
Boss,
we look like total losers!
Why should we keep following this girl?
あんな:such (about something or someone distant from both speaker and listener, or about a situation unfamiliar to both speaker and listener)/so/that, あんな:Anna or Anwa era (968.8.13-970.3.25), のこのこ:unconcernedly/nonchalantly/shamelessly
（ガチャギリ）なんで あんな女に
のこのこついてくんだ
There's no way she's telling the truth.
どうせ:anyhow/in any case|at best, 決まる[きまる]:to be decided/to be settled|to look good in (clothes)
どうせウソに決まってるぜ
鉱脈[こうみゃく]:vein (of ore)/reef/streak, ほとんど:mostly/nearly/practically, 残る[のこる]:to remain/to be left
（ダイチ）メタバグの鉱脈は
もうほとんど残ってないはずだ
There aren't supposed to be any metabug lodes left around here any more.
大量[たいりょう]:large quantity/massive (quantity)/mass (e.g. mass production, mass transit, mass destruction)
大量にあるって
どこなのか知りたくないか？
But if there is a big lode, don't you wanna know where it is?
Stop.
止まる[とまる]:to stop (moving)|to stop (doing, working, being supplied)|to alight, 止まる[とどまる]:to remain/to abide|to be limited to
（イサコ）止まれ！
命令[めいれい]:order/command|(software) instruction, 口調[くちょう]:tone (e.g. of voice, etc.)/(verbal) expression
（ナメッチ）なんか命令口調っすね
She always sounds like she's giving orders!
You guys have heard about what happened at the station building, right?
駅[えき]:station, 事件[じけん]:event/affair/incident
（ダイチ）
お前ら 駅ビルの事件 聞いただろ？
The station?
駅[えき]:station
駅ビル？
工事中[こうじちゅう]:under construction, 空間[くうかん]:space/room/airspace, 空間[あきま]:vacancy/room for rent or lease, 破綻[はたん]:failure/bankruptcy
ああ 工事中の空間が
破綻したやつか
Oh, you mean when that Space under construction crashed?
That happens a lot at construction sites, y'know.
工事[こうじ]:construction work/construction/work (related to construction, e.g. painting, concrete-pouring, etc.), 現場[げんば, げんじょう]:actual spot/scene|shop floor
工事現場では よくあるって言うな
Yeah, but...
事故[じこ, ことゆえ]:accident/incident|circumstances, らしい:seeming ... (expresses judgment based on evidence, reason or trustworthy hearsay)/appearing ...|-ish
それがな ただの事故じゃ
なかったらしい
I don't think it was an accident like the others.
Isn't that right, Akira?
そうだよな？　アキラ
Akira, is that true?
どういう:somehow/how/in what way
なんだよ アキラ どういうことだよ
原因[げんいん]:cause/origin/source, らしい:seeming ... (expresses judgment based on evidence, reason or trustworthy hearsay)/appearing ...|-ish
あれは あの女が原因らしい
Apparently, the cause of it was that girl.
What?
（ガチャギリ）
何？　しかし なんのために…
But what for?
For metabugs!
（ダイチ）メタバグだよ！
空間[くうかん]:space/room/airspace, 空間[あきま]:vacancy/room for rent or lease, 大量[たいりょう]:large quantity/massive (quantity)/mass (e.g. mass production, mass transit, mass destruction), 噴き出す[ふきだす]:to spout out|to sprout|to burst into laughter||, たって:strongly hoping or requesting (of something that is difficult to be brought to fruition), たって:even if/even though|however, 話[はなし]:talk/speech|discussions, 話[わ]:counter for stories, episodes of TV series, etc.
何もない空間から大量のメタバグが
噴き出したって話だ
She actually dug out tons of
metabugs from an empty Space.
R-Really?
ホント:truth/reality/actuality
ホ… ホントっすか？
But the Space tore itself to pieces because of that.
代わり[かわり]:substitute|stand-in|compensation||, 代わり[がわり]:substitute for ..., 空間[くうかん]:space/room/airspace, 空間[あきま]:vacancy/room for rent or lease, ズタボロ:in tatters/in pieces/wiped out
その代わり
空間はズタボロってわけよ
Do you remember a few years back,
空間[くうかん]:space/room/airspace, 空間[あきま]:vacancy/room for rent or lease
ほれ 何年か前
どこかの空間がぶっ壊れて
when after a Space failed, loads of metabugs spilled out?
ザクザク:walking on frost/crunching (e.g. on gravel), 噴き出す[ふきだす]:to spout out|to sprout|to burst into laughter||
メタバグがザクザク噴き出しただろ
Anyway,
空間[くうかん]:space/room/airspace, 空間[あきま]:vacancy/room for rent or lease, 引き換え[ひきかえ]:exchange/conversion, 引き出す[ひきだす]:to pull out/to take out/to draw out, 技術[ぎじゅつ]:technology|technique|art
（ダイチ）
とにかく 空間と引き換えに
メタバグを引き出す技術があるんだ
there's a technique for exchanging parts of the Space for metabugs.
And that girl knows how to do it!
秘密[ひみつ]:secret|secret|esoteric teachings, 握る[にぎる]:to clasp|to make (nigirizushi, rice ball, etc.)|to seize (power, etc.)
あの女は
その秘密を握ってるってことよ
I see!
なるほど:I see/That's right!/Indeed
ん～ なるほど！
Things are getting interesting!
面白い[おもしろい]:interesting|amusing|pleasant
こりゃあ 面白くなってきたぜ
We have to pretend to obey her,
従う[したがう]:to abide (by the rules)/to obey/to follow, フリをする:to pretend, 秘密[ひみつ]:secret|secret|esoteric teachings, 探る[さぐる]:to feel around for|to investigate|to explore (parts unknown)
あいつに従うフリをして
その秘密を探るのだ
and discover her secret!
Got it?
ラジャー:roger/I understand
（ダイチ）いいな？
（一同）ラジャー！
Roger!
Hey!
地図[ちず]:map, なさる:to do
（イサコ）
そこ 地図を出しなさい！
Take out the maps!
命令[めいれい]:order/command|(software) instruction
チェッ 命令してんじゃねえよ
Stop giving us orders already...
手なずける[てなずける, てなづける]:to tame|to win over, カッコ:parentheses/brackets, カッコ:shape/form/figure, 悪い[わるい]:bad|evil|unprofitable||, 悪い[にくい]:hateful/abominable|amazing
（フミエ）あ～あ
手なずけられちゃってカッコ悪い
He's totally whipped.
What a loser!
Hey, tell me more about that story.
さっき:some time ago/just now, さっき:thirst for blood/bloodlust/determination to kill, 話[はなし]:talk/speech|discussions, 話[わ]:counter for stories, episodes of TV series, etc., もっと:(some) more/even more/longer, 教える[おしえる]:to teach|to tell|to preach
（ヤサコ）
ねえ さっきの話 もっと教えてよ
Oh? The one about the Biology Club?
生物[せいぶつ]:living things/creature|biology, 生物[なまもの]:raw food/perishables
ああ 生物部の？
We had some upper classmen with us last year,
上級生[じょうきゅうせい]:student in a higher grade/upperclassman, おとなしい:obedient/docile/quiet
５年のときは上級生もいたから
今よりは おとなしくしてたのよ
so Daichi and his group were better behaved.
But when we started sixth grade,
すっかり:all/completely/totally, 主導権[しゅどうけん]:hegemony/leadership/initiative, 奪う[うばう]:to snatch away/to dispossess/to steal
でも６年になって ダイチに
すっかり主導権 奪われてさ
Daichi pretty much took over.
He became the club president for a while.
一度[いちど, ひとたび]:once|temporarily|one degree, 部長[ぶちょう]:head (chief, director) of a section or department|head of a (school) club/head of a (school) team
一度 ダイチが部長になったの
That's when the club turned into a pranksters club.
電脳[でんのう]:computer|cyberbrain/digital brain, イタズラ:mischief/prank/trick
そしたら
電脳イタズラ部になっちゃってさ
He single-handedly took down the school's server,
学校[がっこう]:school, サーバー:server, ダウン:down (opposite of up)/becoming lower/being brought down, 大目玉[おおめだま]:good scolding
学校のサーバーを
ダウンさせちゃって大目玉
and got a good scolding.
I see.
なるほど:I see/That's right!/Indeed, 想像[そうぞう]:imagination/guess, やすい:cheap/inexpensive|calm, やすい:easy|likely to .../have a tendency to ...
なるほどね 想像しやすいわ
I can easily imagine.
So in the end,
退部[たいぶ]:leaving a club/quitting a club
で 退部になったんだけど
they had to quit the club.
あいつらも
ゾロゾロついてっちゃったわけ
What about Haraken?
ハラケン君は？
He's not very likeable, you know,
実力[じつりょく]:(real) ability/true strength|arms, ないし:emperor's secret orders, ないし:from ... to/between ... and|or, 気[き]:spirit|nature|motivation||, 気[げ]:seeming/giving the appearance of/giving one the feeling of, 弱い[よわい]:weak/frail/delicate
（フミエ）あいつは ほら
実力ないし気が弱いから
and he's also pretty shy.
So I ran for the position.
立候補[りっこうほ]:announcing candidacy/becoming a candidate/bidding (to host an event e.g. Olympics, World Cup)
で 私が立候補したんだけど
But the advisor, Maiko-sensei, chose him instead!
顧問[こもん]:adviser/advisor/consultant, 先生[せんせい, せんじょう]:teacher|with names of teachers, etc. as an honorific|previous existence, 先生[シーサン]:boy, 指名[しめい]:name/nominate/designate
顧問のマイコ先生は
ハラケンを指名したの
I don't understand why!
訳[わけ]:conclusion from reasoning, judgement or calculation based on something read or heard/reason/cause, 訳[やく]:translation/version (e.g. "English version")
訳 分からないわ
Even though I could lead the club with my sheer strength!
強力[きょうりょく]:powerful/strong, 強力[ごうりき]:herculean strength/mountain carrier-guide, 引っ張る[ひっぱる]:to pull|to string (lines)|to pull towards oneself (e.g. someone's sleeve)||, いける:to arrange (flowers)/to plant|living, いける:to be good (at)/to go well|to look (taste, etc.) good
私なら強力に
部を引っ張っていけるのに！
In order to show her I was serious,
公約[こうやく]:public commitment/public promise/campaign pledge, 部長[ぶちょう]:head (chief, director) of a section or department|head of a (school) club/head of a (school) team
公約も 私が部長になったら
I also promised that if I became president, I'd make Daichi and his friends regret it!
コテンパン:black and blue (e.g. beaten ...), やっつける:to beat/to attack (an enemy)/to do away with
“ダイチたちを
コテンパンにやっつけます”って
ちゃんと:diligently/seriously|perfectly
ちゃんと言ったのよ
But Haraken said something noncommittal like,
なんて:how ..!/what ..!|what (questioning), なんて:such as/(things) like|exclamation, 静か[しずか]:quiet|slow|calm, 研究[けんきゅう]:study/research/investigation
ハラケンなんて
“静かに研究したいと思います”
はっきり:clearly/plainly|to be clear
…とか
はっきりしないこと言ってさ
"I'd just like to carry on with my research."
He's got zero leadership skills!
リーダーシップ:leadership
リーダーシップ ゼロよね
先生[せんせい, せんじょう]:teacher|with names of teachers, etc. as an honorific|previous existence, 先生[シーサン]:boy
あ～あ なんでマイコ先生は
ハラケンにしたのかサッパリだわ
I still can't figure out why Maiko-sensei chose Haraken.
Oh, they're on the move!
動く[うごく]:to move|to operate|to be touched||
あっ 動き出した
I think I understand Maiko-sensei's reasons...
先生[せんせい, せんじょう]:teacher|with names of teachers, etc. as an honorific|previous existence, 先生[シーサン]:boy, 気持ち[きもち]:feeling|preparedness|thanks|
マイコ先生の気持ち分かるわ
ハァー
Hey,
おい どこまで行くつもりだよ
how far is it?
What's wrong? Tired?
疲れる[つかれる]:to get tired|to be worn out (e.g. of well used objects)|to starve
何よ 疲れたの？
I never said that!
（ガチャギリ）
そんなこと言ってねえだろ！
The fun part will begin once we're there.
着く[つく]:to arrive at/to reach|to sit on, 着く[はく]:to put on (or wear) lower-body clothing (i.e. pants, skirt, etc.)|to affix a sword to one's hip|to affix a bowstring to a bow, 楽しみ[たのしみ]:enjoyment/pleasure|anticipation, 半分[はんぶん]:half, 半分[はんぷん]:half minute
着いてからのお楽しみよ
まだ半分だわ
We're only halfway.
Wh-What?!
遠い[とおい]:far/distant
（ダイチ）な… 何？
そんなに遠いのかよ！
You never said it was that far!
Let's take a bus. A bus—
バスに乗る[バスにのる]:to take the bus
バスに乗ろうぜ バスに
We'll get on a bus.
乗る[のる]:to get on (train, plane, bus, ship, etc.)|to get on (e.g. a footstool)|to reach||, 着く[つく]:to arrive at/to reach|to sit on, 着く[はく]:to put on (or wear) lower-body clothing (i.e. pants, skirt, etc.)|to affix a sword to one's hip|to affix a bowstring to a bow
乗るわよ バス
着いてからだけど
Once we get there.
It's so hot.
暑い[あつい]:hot (weather, etc.)/warm
ああ… 暑い
You're lucky you can't feel the heat.
暑い[あつい]:hot (weather, etc.)/warm, 感ずる[かんずる]:to feel/to sense
あんたたちはいいわね
暑さを感じなくて
But he looks like he's hot, too.
暑い[あつい]:hot (weather, etc.)/warm
でも暑そうよ
That's because of a demo the pet company is running.
ペット:pet, ペット:polyethylene terephthalate/PET, 会社[かいしゃ]:company/corporation|workplace, 仕掛ける[しかける]:to start|to challenge|to set (traps)
（フミエ）それは
ペット会社の仕掛けたデモよ
I guess they want to start selling fans for cyberpets or something.
どうせ:anyhow/in any case|at best, 電脳[でんのう]:computer|cyberbrain/digital brain, 扇風機[せんぷうき]:electric fan, 売りつける[うりつける]:to palm off/to force a sale, 気[き]:spirit|nature|motivation||, 気[げ]:seeming/giving the appearance of/giving one the feeling of
どうせ また
電脳扇風機でも売りつける気よ
Isn't that right, Haraken?
ねっ？　ハラケン
I don't know.
知らないよ
You know, Haraken's father
お父さん[おとうさん, おとっさん]:father/dad/papa, ペット:pet, ペット:polyethylene terephthalate/PET, メーカー:manufacturer/maker, 勤める[つとめる]:to work (for)|to serve (as)|to conduct a religious service
ハラケンのお父さんはね
ペットのメーカーに勤めてんのよ
works for the manufacturer's company.
That's why he knows so much about cyberpets.
ペット:pet, ペット:polyethylene terephthalate/PET, 詳しい[くわしい]:detailed/full|knowing very well
だから ペットにも
ちょっと詳しいの
へえー
So what kind of pet do you have?
ペット:pet, ペット:polyethylene terephthalate/PET, どんな:what/what kind of|(with -temo, demo, etc.) any(body, thing, means, etc.)
ハラケン君のペットってどんなの？
いるんでしょ？
You have one, right?
I do.
（ハラケン）いるよ
Did you bring it with you today?
連れる[つれる]:to lead/to take (a person)
今日は連れてこないの？
He belongs to my aunt.
（ハラケン）オバちゃんのだから
Oh, they're moving.
動く[うごく]:to move|to operate|to be touched||
あっ 動き出した
What's wrong, Denpa?
デンパ:electromagnetic wave/radio wave/reception
どうしたの？　デンパさん
Oh, a metabug.
あっ メタバグだ
Yeah, it sounds like a wind chime.
風鈴[ふうりん]:wind chime/wind bell, みたい:-like/sort of/similar to, 音がする[おとがする]:to make a sound/to give off a sound|to hear a sound
うん 風鈴みたいな音がする
It has such a beautiful sound.
キレイ:pretty/lovely/beautiful, 音[おと, ね]:sound|note|fame|
キレイな音だよ
I don't hear anything.
聞こえる[きこえる]:to be heard/to be audible|to be said to be
何も聞こえないよ
You can have it.
あげる:to raise/to elevate|to do up (one's hair), 内緒[ないしょ, ないしょう]:secrecy|one's circumstances (esp. fiscal)|inner realization|
あげる　ダイチには内緒だよ
Just don't tell Daichi.
Th-Thank you.
ありがとう:Thank you/Thanks
あ… ありがとう
Hey Fumie, why don't you get along with Daichi?
仲[なか]:relation/relationship, 仲[すあい, すわい]:broker/brokerage/brokerage fee, 悪い[わるい]:bad|evil|unprofitable||, 悪い[にくい]:hateful/abominable|amazing
（ヤサコ）
ねえ なんでフミエちゃんは
ダイチと仲が悪いの？
It's not like I don't get along with him...
仲[なか]:relation/relationship, 仲[すあい, すわい]:broker/brokerage/brokerage fee, 悪い[わるい]:bad|evil|unprofitable||, 悪い[にくい]:hateful/abominable|amazing
（フミエ）
仲が悪いってわけじゃないけど
Both of us have been in the same school since kindergarten.
幼稚園[ようちえん]:kindergarten, 一緒[いっしょ]:together|at the same time|same
あいつとは
幼稚園から一緒なんだけど…
Ah,
あのさ 誰にも言わないでよ
but you can't tell anyone!
Okay.
When we were in the third grade,
頃[ころ, ごろ]:(approximate) time|suitable time (or condition)|time of year, 頃[けい]:qing (Chinese unit of land area equal to 100 mu), しつこい:insistent/obstinate|too rich (taste, etc.), スカート:skirt, してき:historic/historical, してき:pointing out/identification
（フミエ）あいつ ３年の頃さ
しつこくスカートめくりしてきたの
he kept flipping my skirt.
And he was only doing it to me!
それがさ 私だけにするのよ
It got to the point where I thought he was being a total jerk.
もうさ…
“バカか こいつ”って思って
So in order to teach him a lesson, I pulled his shorts down.
仕返し[しかえし]:being even with/reprisal/tit for tat, パンツ:underpants/pants/briefs, 下げる[さげる]:to hang|to lower|to demote|
仕返しに パンツ下げてやったわ
And then,
メガネ:spectacles/glasses, 始める[はじめる]:to start|to open (e.g. a store)|to start ...
（フミエ）
それに私がメガネ始めたら
when I started to play with glasses,
he immediately copied me and got his own.
買う[かう]:to buy|to value|to stir, もらう:to receive/to take|to get somebody to do something
あいつもマネして
すぐ買ってもらって
And then?
（ヤサコ）それで？
He started hacking.
ハッキング:hacking
（フミエ）ハッキングしてくるのよ
He used to draw on my face all the time with a cyberpen!
顔[かお, がん]:face|look|honor|, 顔[かんばせ]:countenance/visage|face, 電脳[でんのう]:computer|cyberbrain/digital brain, イタズラ:mischief/prank/trick, 書く[かく]:to write/to compose|to draw, してき:historic/historical, してき:pointing out/identification
顔に電脳イタズラ書き
してきたりして
So, he only bothered you at the time, right?
ばっかり:only/merely|approximately, ちょっかい:meddling/interference|extending a paw to drag something closer, かける:to hang (e.g. picture)/to hoist (e.g. sail)|to sit, かける:to run (race, esp. horse)/to dash|to gallop (one's horse)
（ヤサコ）
それもフミエちゃんばっかりに
ちょっかいかけてくるのね？
Yeah, you're dead on.
（フミエ）よく分かったわね
That's right.
ばっか:only/merely|approximately
そうなのよ
私にばっかやってくんのよ
He was always doing those things just to me!
And what did you do then?
で どうしたの？
Needless to say, I got back at him by hacking.
もちろん:of course/certainly/naturally, ハッキング:hacking, 仕返し[しかえし]:being even with/reprisal/tit for tat
もちろん
ハッキングで仕返ししてやったわ
That was how I brushed up on my hacking skills.
おかげ:grace (of God)/benevolence (of Buddha)|assistance, ハッキング:hacking, 腕が上がる[うでがあがる]:to gain in skill/to improve/to get better
おかげで
ハッキングの腕が上がった
Hey, what's with that smirk on your face?
ニヤニヤ:grinning/smirking
何？　何ニヤニヤしてんの？
Fumie, you're very dense, you know.
鈍感[どんかん]:thickheaded/insensitive/dull
フミエちゃんって鈍感なのね
Dense about what?
なんのこと？
Look.
見て
Th-This place...
こ… これは
...is a bus graveyard!
墓場[はかば]:graveyard/cemetery
バスの墓場だ
This is cyberfog, isn't it?
電脳[でんのう]:computer|cyberbrain/digital brain, 霧[きり]:fog/mist|spray
（ダイチ）これは電脳霧だよな？
駅[えき]:station, はざま:interval/space|valley, 交差点[こうさてん]:crossing/intersection
駅ビルや はざま交差点に出る
This fog comes out in the station buildings or in the loophole nexus.
はざま:interval/space|valley, 都市[とし]:town/city/municipal, 伝説[でんせつ]:tradition/legend/folklore
（ナメッチ）
はざまって都市伝説の？
The loophole? The one the urban legends talk about?
So is Miss Michiko coming out?
じゃあ ミチコさん出るんすか？
No way.
言える[いえる]:to be possible to say/to be able to say, くだる:to descend/to go down|to be handed down (of an order, judgment, etc.), 迷信[めいしん]:superstition/superstitious belief, 持ち出す[もちだす]:to take out/to carry out|to mention something
バカ言え
くだらない迷信 持ち出すな
She's just like any other business woman.
Denpa,
デンパ:electromagnetic wave/radio wave/reception
デンパさん どうしたの？
what's wrong?
頭[とう]:counter for large animals (e.g. head of cattle), 頭[あたま, かしら]:head|hair (on one's head)|mind||, 痛い[いたい]:painful/sore|exceeding
頭 痛い
My head hurts.
Hey, guys!
足元[あしもと, そっか]:at one's feet|gait|most recent|, なさる:to do
（イサコ）
あんたたち 足元 見てみなさいよ
Take a look at the ground.
M-Metabugs!
メ… メタバグだ！
イヒヒ:hee-hee/tee-hee
（３人）イヒヒ！
Don't waste your time
チンケ:worst/poor and boring/uncool, 拾う[ひろう]:to pick up/to find/to gather
そんなチンケなもの
拾ってんじゃないわよ
on the small fry.
こっちよ
Follow me.
So how long will this tag last?
くらい:dark/gloomy|dark (in colour), くらい:approximately/about|to (about) the extent that
（ヤサコ）
ねえ これ どのくらいもつの？
（フミエ）２～３時間ね
Two or three hours.
During that time,
以内[いない]:within/inside of/less than, 霧[きり]:fog/mist|spray, 体[からだ]:body|torso|build||, 体[たい]:body|shape|substance||, 壊れる[こわれる]:to be broken/to break|to fall through
それ以内なら
霧の中でも体は壊れないわ
he won't break down, even in the middle of this fog.
とはいえ:though/although/be that as it may
ふむ クズバグとはいえ
まだ こんなにあったとは…
Even though they're just rubbish-bugs,
there sure are lots of them.
So what's this fog?
霧[きり]:fog/mist|spray
（ヤサコ）
ねえ この霧ってなんなの？
It's a loss of image that occurs when the Space becomes unstable.
空間[くうかん]:space/room/airspace, 空間[あきま]:vacancy/room for rent or lease, 不安定[ふあんてい]:instability/insecurity/crankiness, 画像[がぞう]:image/picture/portrait, 損失[そんしつ]:loss (e.g. assets or profits)
（フミエ）空間が不安定なときに
出る画像の損失なのよ
黒い[くろい]:black|dark|illicit, 穴が開く[あながあく]:to have a hole/to be pierced (with a hole), 安定[あんてい]:stability/steadiness/equilibrium
ヒドくなると黒い穴が開くんだけど
ここは なぜか安定してるわね
In the worst situations, dark gaps open up.
But it's stable here for some reason.
It's like a loophole.
はざま:interval/space|valley, みたい:-like/sort of/similar to
（ハラケン）はざまみたいだね
Hey,
気味[きみ, きび]:sensation/feeling|tendency, 気味[ぎみ]:-like/-looking/-looked, 悪い[わるい]:bad|evil|unprofitable||, 悪い[にくい]:hateful/abominable|amazing
ちょっと！
気味の悪いこと言わないでよ
stop saying creepy things like that.
どうかしたの？
Is something wrong?
No,
（ハラケン）いや なんでもない
it's nothing.
It's amazing that there are so many metabugs.
（ダイチ）
まだ こんなにあったとはな…
If we search carefully, we'll probably find the big ones.
探す[さがす]:to search (for something desired, needed)/to look for|to search (for something lost), 大粒[おおつぶ]:large grain/large drop
（アキラ）
探せば 大粒のもありそうですね
But it'll be hard to find them in the middle of all these rubbish-bugs.
かえって:on the contrary/rather/all the more, 探す[さがす]:to search (for something desired, needed)/to look for|to search (for something lost), にくい:hateful/abominable|amazing, にくい:difficult to .../hard to ...
（ガチャギリ）
だが クズバグがこうも多いと
かえって探しにくい
Maybe this place has been abandoned.
放置[ほうち]:leaving as is/leaving alone/leaving to chance
（ダイチ）
それで放置されてたのかもな
Not even kids
所[ところ, とこ]:place|address|district||, 所[しょ]:counter for places, 目当て[めあて]:mark|purpose|sight (on a firearm), 子供[こども]:child/children, めった:thoughtless/reckless|seldom (with neg. verb)
こんな所 メタバグ目当ての子供も
めったに来ないぜ
looking for metabugs would come to a place like this.
Well, maybe kids don't,
子供[こども]:child/children, ともかく:anyhow/anyway/somehow or other
子供は ともかく サッチーは？
but what about Satchii?
You guys coming?
入ったら？
What's wrong?
怖い[こわい]:scary/frightening|(I'm) afraid
どうしたの？　怖いの？
Scared?
Sh-Shut up!
うるさい:noisy/loud|annoying
う… うるせえ！
You're just a girl, so—
いちいち:one-by-one/separately|every single
女のくせに
いちいちナメたこと…
どわっ！
D-Daichi!
メガネ:spectacles/glasses, 取る[とる]:to take|to steal|to eat||
ダ… ダイチさん
メガネ取って見て！
Look at the floor without your glasses!
The data gathered here is obsolete.
情報[じょうほう]:information/news|information, 古い[ふるい]:old (not person)/aged/ancient
（アキラ）情報が古いままなんだ
I see.
場所[ばしょ]:place|room|basho, データ:data/datum, 更新[こうしん]:renewal/update/innovation
（ガチャギリ）
そうか 誰も来ない場所だから
データがいつまでも更新されずに…
Since nobody comes here,
the data was never updated...
Turn off your data update settings.
データ:data/datum, 更新[こうしん]:renewal/update/innovation, 停止[ていし, ちょうじ]:suspension/interruption|suspension of music, dance, etc. as a sign of mourning for a prominent person, 設定[せってい]:establishment/creation|options setting, なさる:to do
データの更新を停止に設定しなさい
As the floor's data went off, so did the metabugs.
床[とこ]:bed|sickbed|alcove||, 床[ゆか]:floor|stage (for the narrator and the shamisen player)|dining platform built across a river, なくなる:to die, なくなる:to be lost (e.g. luggage)/to be missing|to be used up, 消える[きえる]:to go out/to vanish/to disappear, しまう:to finish/to stop|to close (a business, etc.)
床がなくなって
メタバグも消えてしまうわよ
（ダイチ）何？
What?
Metabugs always get piled up in a Space's loss or its gaps.
空間[くうかん]:space/room/airspace, 空間[あきま]:vacancy/room for rent or lease, 壊れる[こわれる]:to be broken/to break|to fall through, たまる:to collect/to gather/to save, たまる:to be saved up (e.g. money)
（イサコ）メタバグは
空間の壊れやズレにたまるものよ
Like below this floor.
床[とこ]:bed|sickbed|alcove||, 床[ゆか]:floor|stage (for the narrator and the shamisen player)|dining platform built across a river
この床の下とかね
Anyway,
（ヤサコ）にしても イサコは―
I wonder why Isako brought Daichi's group with her.
担ぎ出す[かつぎだす]:to carry something out of a place|to elevate (someone) to a high position|to mention something, かしら:I wonder, かしら:head|hair (on one's head)
なんでダイチたちを
担ぎ出したのかしら？
Downloading Restore
Who knows?
力仕事[ちからしごと]:physical work/manual labour (labor), 気[き]:spirit|nature|motivation||, 気[げ]:seeming/giving the appearance of/giving one the feeling of
さあ？
力仕事でもさせる気なんでしょ
Complete
I guess she wants them to do the hard work.
ワン！
What's this?
（ダイチ）なんだ これは？
Dig under the floor.
床[とこ]:bed|sickbed|alcove||, 床[ゆか]:floor|stage (for the narrator and the shamisen player)|dining platform built across a river, 掘る[ほる]:to dig|to delve into|to dig up (e.g. vegetables)|, なさる:to do, ザクザク:walking on frost/crunching (e.g. on gravel), 埋まる[うまる, うずまる]:to be buried|to overflow|to be repaid (e.g. debt)
床を掘りなさい
メタバグがザクザク埋まってるわ
There are tons of metabugs down there.
（一同）わあー！
（ダイチ）なんだって？
Really?!
Perhaps.
多分[たぶん]:perhaps/probably|generous
多分ね
What on earth are those guys doing?
一体[いったい]:...the heck (e.g. "what the heck?")|one object|one form||, かしら:I wonder, かしら:head|hair (on one's head)
あいつら
一体 何してるのかしら？
It looks like they're digging inside the bus.
掘る[ほる]:to dig|to delve into|to dig up (e.g. vegetables)|, みたい:-like/sort of/similar to
（ヤサコ）
バスの中を掘ってるみたい
Well? Nothing's coming out!
クソッ なんも出ねえじゃねえか
Oh, sorry.
悪い[わるい]:bad|evil|unprofitable||, 悪い[にくい]:hateful/abominable|amazing, 間違える[まちがえる]:to make a mistake (in)/to commit an error (e.g. in calculation)|to confuse
あっ 悪い　間違えた
My bad.
It's in that bus.
あっち:that way (direction distant from both speaker and listener)/over there|that one (something physically distant from both speaker and listener, or something not visible but known by both speaker and listener)
あっちのバスだ
What?
何？
It's not here either.
次[つぎ]:next/following|stage, 次[じ]:next|hypo- (i.e. containing an element with low valence)|order
ここも違うわね
次 行きましょう
Let's check the next one.
（ナメッチ）ハァ ハァ…
Not here after all.
次[つぎ]:next/following|stage, 次[じ]:next|hypo- (i.e. containing an element with low valence)|order
（イサコ）ここも違うようね 次
Next!
れっか:deterioration/degradation/drop in quality, れっか:raging fire/conflagration
やってられっか！
I've had it!
簡単[かんたん]:simple/easy|brief, 見つかる[みつかる]:to be found/to be discovered
ちょっと ちょっと
簡単に見つかるとでも思ってたの？
Hey, hey.
Did you really think they would be easy to find in the first place?
帰る[かえる]:to return|to leave|to get home
いいのよ ここで帰っても
I don't mind if you want to go home now.
ハァ…
あ～あ…
からかう:to ridicule/to tease/to mock, 壮大[そうだい]:magnificent/grand/majestic, イタズラ:mischief/prank/trick
お前 俺たちをからかうための
壮大なイタズラじゃなかろうな？
Hey,
you didn't plan all this just to play us for fools, did you?
そこ
Over there.
これは…
These...
バグる:to behave buggily (software)/to act up/to behave strangely, サイズ:size
クズバグってサイズじゃないぞ！
...aren't the size of rubbish-bugs!
（イサコ）待ちな！
Hold it!
な… なんだよ
Now what?
（モジョたち）
モジョ モジョ モジョ モジョ…
爆発[ばくはつ]:explosion/detonation/eruption, 性[さが, なりくせ]:one's nature/one's destiny|custom, 性[せい]:nature (of a person)|sex|gender|
こいつは爆発性のやつなのよ
That stuff is explosive.
通販[つうはん]:mail order/online shopping/e-commerce, 買う[かう]:to buy|to value|to stir, 原料[げんりょう]:raw materials
あんたたちが通販で買った
カンシャクの原料よ
It's the raw material for the
firecrackers you bought online.
足元[あしもと, そっか]:at one's feet|gait|most recent|, たっぷり:full/in plenty/ample, 埋まる[うまる, うずまる]:to be buried|to overflow|to be repaid (e.g. debt), 気をつける[きをつける]:to be careful/to pay attention/to take care, なさる:to do
足元にたっぷり埋まってるから
気をつけなさい
There are plenty of them buried right under your feet,
so watch out.
（一同）えー！
（ガチャギリ）ちょっと待てよ
Hey, hold on a sec!
買い取り[かいとり]:purchase|buying used articles as a company|purchase on a no-return policy|, 規約[きやく]:agreement/rules/code
買い取りの規約にあったぞ
In the shop's license agreement,
爆発[ばくはつ]:explosion/detonation/eruption, 性[さが, なりくせ]:one's nature/one's destiny|custom, 性[せい]:nature (of a person)|sex|gender|, 引き取る[ひきとる]:to take over|to take charge of|to retire to a private place
爆発性のメタバグは
引き取れないって
it says that they won't exchange explosive metabugs for money.
（一同）何？
What?!
やっぱり:too/also|still, だます:to trick/to cheat|to coax
やっぱりだましたな！
So you really did trick us!
なさる:to do
（イサコ）よく見なさい
Look carefully.
これは…
This is...
交ざる[まざる]:to be mixed/to be blended with/to associate with, 爆発[ばくはつ]:explosion/detonation/eruption
（イサコ）交ざってるのよ
爆発しないものもね
They're mixed
with the nonexplosive ones.
ホント:truth/reality/actuality
（ガチャギリ）ホントだ
She's right!
数[しばしば]:often/again and again/frequently, 数[かず]:number/amount, 少ない[すくない]:few/a little/scarce, 確か[たしか]:sure|reliable|If I'm not mistaken
数は少ないが確かにある
There aren't many, but there are a few of them for sure.
離れる[はなれる]:to be separated|to leave|to leave (a job, etc.)|, 危ない[あぶない]:dangerous|in danger|uncertain||, 戻る[もどる]:to turn back (e.g. half-way)|to return|to recover (e.g. something lost)|, 戻る[もとる]:to go against/to act contrary to/to deviate from
離れたら危ないよ　戻ろう
Don't go too far. It's dangerous.
Let's head back.
暑い[あつい]:hot (weather, etc.)/warm
ひぃ… 暑い
It's so hot!
マズい:unappetising|unskillful|ugly|, 電波[でんぱ, デムパ]:electromagnetic wave/radio wave|saying strange things, 状態[じょうたい]:current status/condition/situation, 悪い[わるい]:bad|evil|unprofitable||, 悪い[にくい]:hateful/abominable|amazing, すぎる:to pass through/to pass by|to pass (i.e. of time)
マ… マズいぞ！
電波状態が悪すぎる
Crap!
We're almost out of the network signal's range.
霧[きり]:fog/mist|spray, 影響[えいきょう]:influence/effect|to influence, 電波[でんぱ, デムパ]:electromagnetic wave/radio wave|saying strange things, 状態[じょうたい]:current status/condition/situation, 所[ところ, とこ]:place|address|district||, 所[しょ]:counter for places, 集まる[あつまる]:to gather/to collect/to assemble
き… 霧の影響だ
みんな 電波状態のいい所に集まれ
It must be the effect of the fog.
Let's all gather where there's a strong signal!
皆[みんな, みな]:all/everyone|everything, 一体[いったい]:...the heck (e.g. "what the heck?")|one object|one form||, まじない:charm/incantation/spell
（アキラ）み… 皆さん
それは 一体なんのおまじないで？
E-Everyone...
What sort of magic are you...?
デンパ:electromagnetic wave/radio wave/reception, 誘電[ゆうでん]:induction/induced electricity|dielectric, 波[なみ]:wave, 波[ぽ]:Poland, 体質[たいしつ]:constitution (physical)/genetic make-up|structure (e.g. of an organization), 電波[でんぱ, デムパ]:electromagnetic wave/radio wave|saying strange things, 受信[じゅしん]:reception (e.g. radio)/receipt (e.g. email message), 感度[かんど]:sensitivity/reception (e.g. radio and television)/severity (quake), 高い[たかい]:high/tall|expensive
（ダイチ）
デンパは誘電波体質といって
電波の受信感度が高いのだ
Denpa is a good wave conductor,
Denpa's nickname also sounds like "radio wave".
so his signal receptivity is very high.
デンパ:electromagnetic wave/radio wave/reception, 体[からだ]:body|torso|build||, 体[たい]:body|shape|substance||, 壊れる[こわれる]:to be broken/to break|to fall through
だから ほれ デンパだけ
体 壊れてないだろ？
As you can see,
Denpa's body is the only one that's intact.
暑い[あつい]:hot (weather, etc.)/warm
ああ… 暑いよ
It's so hot here!
デンパ:electromagnetic wave/radio wave/reception, あだ名[あだな, こんめい]:nickname
そ… それで
デンパってあだ名なんだ
So that's why his nickname's Denpa.
張り付く[はりつく]:to stick (to)/to cling (to)|to stay (e.g. in the office), こぼれ:nick/chip/scratch, こぼれ:spilling/spill|leavings, 文字[もじ, もんじ]:letter (of alphabet)/character|literal, 化け[ばけ]:transforming oneself/taking on another form|artificial fly (for fishing), 治る[なおる]:to be cured/to get well|to get mended
（ナメッチ）張り付くと
おこぼれで文字化けが治るんだ
If you come with us, your net signal will be restored.
お前もこっち来い
C'mere already!
結構[けっこう]:splendid|sufficient|well enough||
い… いえ 結構です
N-No, I'm fine.
よーし:alright/all right/right on, 治る[なおる]:to be cured/to get well|to get mended
よーし 治ったぞ
Okay,
we're restored.
（一同）ハァ…
あれ？
イサコは どこ行ったんすか？
Where did Isako get off to?
あっ トンズラしたのか？
Did she run away?
在る[ある]:to be (usu. of inanimate objects)|to have|to be located||, 用[よう]:business|use|for the use of ...|
メタバグの在りかが分かったら
もう用はねえ
We don't need her now that we know where the metabugs are!
次[つぎ]:next/following|stage, 次[じ]:next|hypo- (i.e. containing an element with low valence)|order, 探す[さがす]:to search (for something desired, needed)/to look for|to search (for something lost)
次を探そうぜ
Let's search the next one!
頭痛[ずつう]:headache, うっとうしい:gloomy (e.g. mood)/depressing|irritating
（イサコ）
この頭痛 うっとうしいな
This headache is such a pain.
（モジョ）モジョ モジョ モジョ
掘る[ほる]:to dig|to delve into|to dig up (e.g. vegetables)|, 台[だい]:stand|support|counter for machines, incl. vehicles||, 台[うてな]:tower|stand|calyx
ヤツらに掘らせたバスは
これで15台
I had them dig in fifteen buses including this one.
個[こ, コ]:counter for articles|counter for military units|individual, 個[か, カ]:counter for the ichi-ni-san counting system (usu. directly preceding the item being counted)/a noun read using its on-yomi, 見つかる[みつかる]:to be found/to be discovered
１個も見つからない
I didn't find a single one.
やはり:too/also|still, 通常[つうじょう]:common/general/normal, 存在[そんざい]:existence/being, 物質[ぶっしつ]:material/substance|matter
やはり通常には
存在しない物質なのか？
Is it possible that this substance doesn't exist in a normal Space?
ハッ！　待てよ
Wait a minute.
エネルギー:energy, 一気[いっき]:chug!/drink! (said repeatedly as a party cheer), 放出[ほうしゅつ]:release/emission/ejection
もし これだけのエネルギーを
一気に放出したら
If I could release all this energy in a single blast...
あるいは:or/possibly
あるいは…
やっぱり:too/also|still, なかなか:very/considerably|by no means (with negative verb), 集まる[あつまる]:to gather/to collect/to assemble, みたい:-like/sort of/similar to
やっぱり
なかなか集まらないみたいね
As I thought, they're collecting a lot of them after all.
うまい:skillful/skilful|delicious, 話[はなし]:talk/speech|discussions, 話[わ]:counter for stories, episodes of TV series, etc.
うまい話はないってことか
So there was no valuable info...
あら そういえばデンスケは？
Eh?
By the way, where's Densuke?
Me Satchii!
（サッチー）ボク サッチー
（ダイチ）あいつら！
Aren't those two...
出たー！
IT'S HERE!
なんだ？
What the—?
（一同）出たー！　出たー！
（サッチー）ボク…
あっ そんな…
Oh no!
メガネ:spectacles/glasses
あっ メガネ メガネ…
My glasses, my glasses...
あった
Here they are!
イヤー:ear
イヤー！
（フミエ）こっちよ！
No!
Hurry up!
早い[はやい]:fast|early (in the day, etc.)|(too) soon|
早く！
連鎖[れんさ]:chain/chaining|(genetic) linkage, 反応[はんのう, はんおう]:reaction/response, 起こす[おこす]:to raise|to wake|to cause||
（イサコ）ここと ここをやれば
連鎖反応が起こせるわ
If I do this here,
and then here...
I can create a chain reaction.
ありがとう:Thank you/Thanks
あ… ありがとう
Th-Thank you...
駅[えき]:station
あんた ダイチに
駅ビルのことチクッたろ！
Did you
tell Daichi
about what happened
at the station?
Please forgive me, Sis!
許す[ゆるす]:to permit|to exempt (from fine)|to confide in|, お姉ちゃん[おねえちゃん]:familiar form of "older sister"|form of address for young adult female
（アキラ）許してよ お姉ちゃん！
お姉ちゃん[おねえちゃん]:familiar form of "older sister"|form of address for young adult female
お姉ちゃん？
Sis?!
我が[わが]:my/our/one's own, 愚弟[ぐてい]:younger brother|stupid younger brother
そう 我が愚弟 アキラよ
Yeah, he's my little brother, Akira.
まったく:really/truly|indeed, 悪事[あくじ]:evil deed/crime/wickedness, 手を染める[てをそめる]:to get involved (with)/to begin (with)/to have a hand (in)
まったく…
こんな年で悪事に手を染めて！
How could you get involved with such bad company at your age?
ここだ
This is the place.
（サッチー）ボク サッチー
Me Satchii!
今後[こんご]:from now on/hereafter, 動き[うごき]:movement/move|trend, 逐一[ちくいち, ちくいつ]:one by one/in detail/minutely, 報告[ほうこく]:report/information
今後はダイチたちの動きを
逐一 報告するのよ
You'll report any details regarding Daichi's movements to me.
いいわね？
Got it?
勘弁[かんべん]:pardon/forgiveness/forbearance, スパイ:spy, なんて:how ..!/what ..!|what (questioning), なんて:such as/(things) like|exclamation
勘弁してよ！
スパイなんてヤダだよ
Please,
I don't wanna be a spy!
（爆発音）
（３人）何？
What was that?!
急ぐ[いそぐ]:to hurry/to rush/to hasten
（フミエ）急いで！
Hurry!
（サッチー）
ボク ボク… サ… サッチー…
M-Me... Me S-Sat—
Sat-chi-chi...
...chi-chi...
Even with all this energy, it's still not working?
エネルギー:energy
これだけのエネルギーがあっても
ダメなのか
B... Boss!
助ける[たすける]:to save|to help|to aid|
オ… オヤビン 助けて！
Help me!
Not good!
残金[ざんきん]:remaining money, 足りる[たりる]:to be sufficient|to be worth doing|to be sufficient
ダメだ 残金が足りねえ
I don't have enough credit left!
大変[たいへん]:very|immense|serious||, てめえ:you (used by young males)|oneself
（イサコ）大変ね
（ダイチ）て… てめえ！
Looks like you're all in trouble.
D-Damn you!
Do you want me to give these to you?
分ける[わける]:to divide (into)|to share|to distinguish||
これ 分けてやろうか？
Do you?
欲しい[ほしい]:wanted/wished for|I want (you) to
欲しい？
Are you serious?
本当か？
In exchange,
代わり[かわり]:substitute|stand-in|compensation||, 代わり[がわり]:substitute for ..., 子分[こぶん]:henchman/follower|adopted child
（イサコ）その代わり
お前たち 私の子分になれ
you'll become my lackeys.
な… なんだと！
What?!
You can refuse, of course.
イヤならいいんだぞ
Boss!
（ナメッチ）
オヤビン ど… どうするんすか？
What should we do?
Damn you...
おめえ:you (formerly honorific, now sometimes derog. term referring to an equal or inferior)|presence (of a god, nobleman, etc.), 最初[さいしょ]:beginning/outset/first
おめえ 最初から
こうするつもりで…
So you had this planned from the beginning?
If you join me, I'll fix your bodies immediately.
体[からだ]:body|torso|build||, 体[たい]:body|shape|substance||, 治す[なおす]:to cure|to fix|to do over again (after -masu base of verb)||
こっちに来れば
すぐに体は治してやる
So what's your choice?
さあ どうする？
ああ～ イサコオヤビ～ン！
Isako, boss!
N-Namecchi!
ナ… ナメッチ！
If you make it worth my while,
金[おうごん, こがね]:gold, 金[かね, かな]:money|metal, 稼ぐ[かせぐ]:to earn (income)|to score (points, victory)|to work hard (at one's job), 構う[かまう]:to mind|to care for|to prepare for||
金を稼がせてくれるんなら
俺も構わねえぜ
I don't mind joining you, too.
ガチャギリ…
Gachagiri...
（デンパ）
ヒ… ヒドいよ ガチャギリ
That's cruel, Gachagiri!
Daichi!
ついていく:to accompany/to follow/to keep up with
ダイチ 僕はダイチについていくよ
I'll always stick by your side!
Tell me.
教える[おしえる]:to teach|to tell|to preach
教えてくれ
Those techniques you're using...
技[わざ, ぎ]:technique/art/skill, もしかし:perhaps/maybe/by some chance
お前の使ってる技って
もしかして…
Are they...
もしかし:perhaps/maybe/by some chance, 暗号[あんごう]:code/password/cipher, 屋[や]:(something) shop|somebody who sells (something) or works as (something)|somebody with a (certain) personality trait||, 技[わざ, ぎ]:technique/art/skill
もしかして 暗号屋の技なのか？
Encoder techniques?
That's right!
そうよ
M-
暗号[あんごう]:code/password/cipher, 屋[や]:(something) shop|somebody who sells (something) or works as (something)|somebody with a (certain) personality trait||, 憧れる[あこがれる]:to long for/to yearn after/to admire
イ… イサコさん
僕 暗号屋に憧れてるんです！
Miss Isako!
I've always wanted to become an Encoder!
Please accept me as your pupil!
弟子[でし, ていし]:pupil/disciple/adherent, くださる:to give/to confer|to kindly do for one
弟子にしてください！
ガーン:boom/bang/wham
ガーン！
大黒[だいこく]:god of wealth|monk's wife, 黒[くろ]:black|black go stone|guilt, 客[きゃく, かく]:guest/visitor|customer, 客[まろうど, まろうと]:visitor from afar/guest, リーダー:leader
今から 私が大黒(だいこく)黒客のリーダーよ
From now on,
I am the leader of the Daikoku Hackers!
Roger!
ラジャー:roger/I understand
（ダイチたち）ラジャー！
I don't have any walls or mega-be left!
壁[かべ, へき]:wall|barrier|Chinese "Wall" constellation (one of the 28 mansions), 残る[のこる]:to remain/to be left
壁もメガビーも残ってないわ
Stop!
（ハラケン）待て！
Stop
Haraken!
（フミエ）ハラケン！
Sit.
座る[すわる]:to sit|to assume (a position)|to hold steady
（ハラケン）お座り
Shake hands.
お手
C'mon, we'll escape while it's like this!
逃げる[にげる]:to escape/to run away
さあ 今のうちに逃げよう
It'll only obey me for a minute.
僕の言うことを聞くのは
１分だけなんだ
Who on earth...
一体[いったい]:...the heck (e.g. "what the heck?")|one object|one form||
あ… あなた 一体…
are you?
何者[なにもの]:who/what kind of person
（フミエ）…何者なの？
Preview
Next time on Dennou Coil:
The Red Automaton.
The Red Automaton
See you next time!
次回[じかい]:next time (occasion), 電脳[でんのう]:computer|cyberbrain/digital brain, コイル:coil
（ヤサコ）
次回 「電脳コイル」
赤い[あかい]:red|Red (i.e. communist), オートマトン:automaton
〝赤いオートマトン 〞
楽しみ[たのしみ]:enjoyment/pleasure|anticipation
お楽しみに